Okay, so in this video then, we are going
to be discussing
qualitative risk analysis.
Perform qualitative risk analysis.
Now, qualitative risk analysis then is
analyzing your risks
based on arbitrary values.
And arbitrary values means things like
high, medium low, scale of 1 to 10,
red, yellow, green classification.
So we're prioritizing and ranking our
risks based on these, you know,
based on these values.
Now, be very careful with qualitative and
quantitative risk analysis.
Quantitative is covered in separate
slides.
With quantitative risk analysis, we are
actually adding in a
dollar value to our risk.
And we're going to be
calculating something called
expected monetary
value and so and so forth.
With qualitative, right, with
this one here, we are prioritized
in ranking our risk based
on these arbitrary values.
high, medium low, scale of 1 to 10,
and so and so forth.
And what does high, medium low mean?
What does scale of 1 to 10 mean?
Well, that's all going to be documented.
That's all going to be defined in the risk
management plan.
So just as an exam tip, make
sure when you're reading a
question, you don't confuse
qualitative and quantitative.
It's very, very easy to do because their
spelling looks very similar, right?
but there are two very, very different
processes.
So here we're talking arbitrary values,
high, medium low, scale of 1 to 10,
red, yellow, green, right?
So it could be percentages and so on and
so forth.
There's a very, very simple formula that
you need to know in this section.
And say someone here,
probability times impact
equals the score, right,
or some kind of risk score.
Now, in the exam, they will
always give you probability,
they will always give you
impact, multiply the two.
numbers together and you get the risk
score.
So this is specifically then for the
qualitative side.
And again, we're using arbitrary values,
high, medium, low, scale of 1 to 10,
and so and so forth.
Right now, you could do the same thing
using a probability and impact matrix,
right, which is covered in a separate
video.
All right, now, let's talk about
probability and impact, right?
Let's talk about this calculation.
I will talk about this on the next slide.
We just want to point out that this last
bullet point here, document a watch list
of low priority risks, we'll cover that in
just a second.
However, let's do some
very simple calculations,
a very simple calculation on qualitative.
So let's say we're using a scale of 1 to
10.
I mean, again, arbitrary
values, scale of 1 to 10, with
1 being the lowest value,
10 being the highest value.
And so remember what the former is,
probability times impact equals the score.
So let's say we've identified a risk,
risk one.
What's the probability of that risk
occurring?
So let's say, you know, we discussed with
our team and we say on a scale of 1 to 10,
the probability of risk one occurring is a
5.
Now, what does that mean?
Well, we have to go to the
risk management plan to
determine what a probability
of 5 actually means.
The risk management plan is defining what
probability five actually means.
On a scale of 1 to 10,
let's say we've figured
out that the impact is going to be a 7.
Again, what does that mean?
Documented in the risk management plan.
So there's just something that we are
discussing with the team.
So we've come up with a probability,
on a scale of 1 to 10, the probability of
risk one occurring is a 5 and the impact
in the 7.
So what's the score?
Just multiply the two together.
Five times 7, the risk score is 35.
Again, what does that mean?
Documented in the risk management plan.
So let's say we've identified another
risk, risk two.
And we think the probability
of that risk occurring on
a scale of 1 to 10 is an
8, much higher probability.
The impact in case it occurs is a 6,
so we have a risk score of 48.
And then we've identified another risk,
risk 3.
The probability of that risk
occurring on a scale of 1 to 10
is 7, and the impact is a 9,
so we give it a risk score of 63.
3.
So we've identified risks 1, 2 and 3.
So what do we want to do now?
We want to rank those risks.
We want to prioritize those risks.
So which of these then is going to be the
highest priority risk?
Well, risk 3, because that's the highest
score.
Risk 3 is going to be the highest priority
risk followed by risk
2, followed by risk 1.
So risk 3 then is the one that we want to
pay the most attention to right now,
because that's the highest priority risk.
And that is literally what this process is
about.
This perform qualitative risk analysis.
This is one of the actual PIMBox 6
processes, which is also in the part of
the new exam as well, part of the new exam
syllabus.
And that is literally what this process
refers to.
It's prioritizing your risk, ranking your
risk, based on these arbitrary values.
Okay.
Now, there's several other factors that
could impact your relative ranking.
And I'm going to come back to Risk 4 in
just a second.
But let me just go to the next
slide here, because, like I said,
this section is all about
prioritizing and ranking your risk.
Well, there's many different factors that
could impact your relative ranking.
Right.
For example, proximity or urgency,
urgency of the risk.
Right.
How close is it a risk?
So the very simple example.
Let's go back to the previous slide.
we have identified risk three as a highest
priority risk.
Why?
Simply because of the risk score of 63.
It's got the highest risk score.
However, what if we also know that this is
a risk that is not going to occur until
deployment and go live, which might not be
until two years from now?
Okay, so it's a high probability,
high impact risk at deployment and go
live, but that's not necessarily a high
probability impact risk right now.
So right now, risk two is something that
might occur within the
next couple of weeks.
So risk two then would be a much higher
priority now than risk three.
So any of these items then could impact
your relative ranking, right, relative
prioritization, the urgency of the risk,
proximity of the risk, right, how well the
risk can be managed or
controlled, right, whether or not
has a strategic impact,
right, that can have an impact.
And then based on
that, you may be creating
some additional
categories of risks as well.
Even stakeholder disperception of the
risk.
That can impact the relative ranking of
the risk as well.
Now, let's go back to this slide and let
me talk about risk four, because we also
want to create a watch list of low
priority risks.
And this was mentioned on the first slide
here.
If I go back, this last bullet point
document, a watch list of low priority risk.
not a watch list of high priority.
High priority risks, it couldn't be
looking at anyway.
It's risk like number four that we want to
keep a track of.
So, for example, risk four has a
probability of two.
Low probability of a risk occurring.
However, if it does occur, it has a huge
impact.
10, on a scale of 1 to 10, it has an
impact of 10.
That is a huge impact on our project.
However, if you look at the risk score,
2 times 10, we give a risk score of 20.
So based on that risk score, we think,
well, that's a low priority risk.
Compared to all the others, that looks
like the lowest priority risk.
Do we want to ignore that risk?
No.
Although it's low probability,
that's a huge impact.
Risk have a tendency of
increasing or decreasing
in probability throughout the project.
So this is a kind of risk then that we
want to put in a watch list.
make sure then we're constantly
referring to this risk, make
sure the probability of that
risk is not increasing, right?
And if it does start increasing, you
know, we need to do something about it.
So that's what qualitative risk analysis
is then, is just literally ranking,
prioritising your risk based on these
arbitrary values.
Okay.